Frank Hamilton Hankins Papers, 1922-1968
Smith College Archives
Frank Hamilton Hankins Papers
1922-1968
Hankins, Frank Hamilton, 1877-
RG 42 UUID:a0058a25-c098-4114-b020-1c1dae74278d
9 boxes (3.75 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of Sociology, demographer, author and lecturer. Contains articles, correspondence, written speeches, photographs, minutes from meetings, and publications.
Frank Hamilton Hankins was born on September 27, 1877 in Wilkshire, Ohio. He grew up in Kansas, where he received an A.B. from Baker University in 1901. He served as superintendent of schools in Waverly, Kansas for two years before entering Columbia University. As a graduate student and fellow in statistics, Hankins was strongly influenced by the philosophy and logic of John Stuart Mill, the sociology of Giddings, Spencer, and Ward, and the quantitative work of Quetelet, Galton, and Pearson. His doctoral dissertation, "Adolphe Quetelet as Statitician" (1908), was an important contribution to the development of empirical sociology.
Hankins served as a member of the Clark University faculty for sixteen years (1906-22), and head of the Department of Political and Social Science beginning in 1908. Clark, at the time, was under the leadership of the influential psychologist G. Stanley Hall, and was visited by famous psychoanalysts such as Sigmund Freud and Havelock Ellis. Thus, it was a center of research, graduate study, and stimulating scholarly controversy. Hankins contributed numerous articles to scholarly journals, lectured frequently at other universities, studied social conditions in Europe before and after World War I, and taught at the Ecole Libre des Sciences Politique in Paris in 1921.
Hankins joined the Smith College faculty in 1922 as Professor of Sociology, and for many years he served as department chairman, until he left Smith in 1946. Under the presidency of William Allan Neilson, Smith was an exciting and non-cloistered campus. Hankins, in his years at Smith, built up an excellent group of sociologists on campus, which included people such as Harry Elmer Barnes, Ray Billington, G.A. Borgese, Merle Curti, and Harold Faulkner, among others. Hankins was very active on many different boards and organizations on population and individual rights. In 1930, Hankins was elected the first President of the American Sociological Society, and in 1945 President of the American Population Association. He also taught and lectured widely, serving on the faculties of Amherst College, Columbia, Berkeley, the Army Center at Biarritz, and, following his retirement from Smith, the University of Pennsylvania. In 1936, he studied, on the scene, social conditions in Nazi Germany.
Hankins contributed widely to scholarly journals, anthologies, and the Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences. His ground-breaking study, The Racial Basis of Civilization: A Critique of the Nordic Doctrine, was published in 1926. In 1928, he published An Introduction to the Study of Society, a textual treatise presenting his principal theoretical and substantive concerns and convictions. Hankins' writings reveal a keen interest in the role of biological factors in social life and history and, conversely, in the role of such selective processes as urbanization, education, persecution, and war in the determination of population quantity and quality. He argued in favor of birth control, more for the lower classes and less for the privileged. He condemned authoritarian institutions and practices and supported the maximization of opportunity for all. He also denounced racist policies and believed that racially mixed populations were physically and socially beneficial.
Hankins died of a heart attack at the age of 92 on January 24, 1970 in Franklin Lakes, New Jersey. At the time of his death, he was an eminent sociologist and demographer, distinguished author and lecturer, provocative and influential teacher, an ardent proponent of a strictly scientific sociology, and a concerned humanist.
The Frank Hamilton Hankins Papers span a period from 1922 to 1968, and much of the material is composed of his numerous publications. The collection also covers his involvement in various societies and organizations. The folders are arranged alphabetically, and the hefty folders full of letters and notes regarding Hankins' various organizations point to his involvement in the sociological world. Overall, the Frank Hamilton Hankins Papers are composed of articles, correspondence, written speeches, photographs, minutes from meetings, publications, and information from Hankins' time at different universities, such as Columbia and Clark.
In addition to some chronologies of Hankins' history, the biographical materials also contain some articles and press releases at the time of his death. Much of the information is repetitious, but they are a good source of factual insight.
The correspondence and subject files include the many letters Hankins wrote to his peers over the years, on general subjects as well as specific ones. In addition to general correspondence, there is one box of material devoted specifically to the correspondence between Hankins and his colleague Harry Elmer Barnes. This series also contains several subject files of a variety of topics.
Copies of Hankins' publications comprise the largest part of this collection. There is some information on debates Hankins was involved with and lectures he gave. Also, there are some materials on Hankins' contributions to The New Humanist, a journal that aims to cover unrestricted and liberal viewpoints. Hankins' collaboration with Farrar & Rinehart Publishers is also well documented. This file includes correspondence, notes, monetary agreements, and memorandums. Apparently, Hankins was editing several textbooks on sociology. There also seems to be a paper on Hankins' thoughts on American Development.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. Correspondence
III. Subject Files/Organizations
IV. Speeches/Publications
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
Search Terms
Hankins, Frank Hamilton, 1877-; Smith College--Faculty.; Clark University (Worcester, Mass.)--Faculty.; Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1889-1968.; Bryson, Gladys, 1894-1952.; Marsh, Margaret S., 1945-; Phelps, Harold Augustus, 1898-; Faris, Ellsworth, 1874-
- Series I. Biographical Materials
  The first series, Biographical Materials, contains several summaries of Hankins' life. Several newspapers, such as the Boston Globe and the Daily Hampshire Gazette, carried articles on Hankins' death. There are also some of what appear to be press releases from the Smith College Office of Publicity regarding Hankins and his activities in the community. One folder also contains several photographs of Hankins and his wife, as well as Hankins instructing a student.
  - BIOGRAPHICAL DATA (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. Subject Files and Organizations
  There are approximately two and a half boxes devoted to the second series, Correspondence. Hankins wrote to many people, especially his colleague Harry Elmer Barnes. The correspondence between Hankins and Barnes covers a period from the early 1920's to the late 1960's. Both men often helped each other in their work and exchanged opinions. The other letters cover a range of subjects, from Hankins' academic work to more personal notes. The correspondence is especially rich in the 1930s. A vast majority of the correspondence is typed and reflect Hankins' involvement in a large variety of organizations. There are also several folders of congratulatory letters and cards wishing Hankins a happy 70th, 90th, and 91st birthday.
  - AMERICAN COMMITTEE FOR DEMOCRACY AND INTELLECTUAL FREEDOM (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AMERICAN DEVELOPMENT (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AMERICAN EUGENICS SOCIETY 1937-38 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AMERICAN EUGENICS SOCIETY 1939-48 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AMERICAN EUGENICS SOCIETY - TEXTBOOK (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AMERICAN SOCIOLOGICAL SOCIETY (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CLARK UNIVERSITY (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - CLARK UNIVERSITY - DEGREES (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - CLARK UNIVERSITY - SCHOLARSHIP (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - CORNELL UNIVERSITY (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - CORRESPONDENCE 1922-67 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - BIRTHDAY 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - BIRTHDAY 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - BIRTHDAY 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - BARNES, HARRY ELMER (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - BRYSON, GLADYS (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - MARSH, MARGARET (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - TEAGLE, ALICE 1904 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - CORRESPONDENCE 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - DEBATES (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - FARRAR & RINEHART (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - FELLOWSHIPS (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - GENERAL (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - HUMANIST MANIFESTO (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - LECTURES (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - MACMILLAN COMPANY (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - NORTHAMPTON - TERCENTENARY (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - ORAL HISTORY (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - OREGON UNIVERSITY (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - PLANNED PARENTHOOD - BIRTH CONTROL RESEARCH (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - PLANNED PARENTHOOD - SANGER (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - POPULATION ASSOCIATION OF AMERICA (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - POPULATION REFERENCE BUREAU 1935-49 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - POPULATION REFERENCE BUREARU 1946 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - POPULATION REFERENCE BUREAU 1950-52 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - POPULATION REFERENCE BUREAU 1953-54 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - QUESTIONNAIRE (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - RETIREMENT (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - SHANGHAI, CHINA (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - SOCIOLOGY DEPARTMENT 1939-42 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - SMITH COLLEGE SCHOOL FOR SOCIAL WORK (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - SOCIAL FORCES (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - SOCIOLOGY DEPARTMENT - LECTURES (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - SOCIOLOGY DEPARTMENT - SURVEY SOCIAL SCIENCE (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - SOCIOLOGY DEPARTMENT - MAJORS (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - SPEECHES (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - SPEECHES - GET TOGETHER CLUB (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - TECHNICAL AID DILEMMA (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series III. Correspondence
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Subject Files and Organizations covers a broad range of topics, from Hankins' involvement in the American Eugenics Society to the development of the Sociology department. There are also several folders on the various universities Hankins taught at, such as Clark University, Columbia University, and Cornell University. Descriptions of scholarships and fellowships are also included. Looking through these various subject files, it is easy to get a general idea of Hankins. He was obviously interested in such topics as eugenics and population control. His participation in the American Committee for Democracy and Intellectual Freedom, the American Eugenics Society, and the American Sociological Society is extensively covered. These folders are largely composed of correspondence, but also include essays and a scrapbook.
  - CORRESPONDENCE 1936 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - CORRESPONDENCE Jan-May 1937 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - CORREPONDENCE June-Dec 1937 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Phelps, Harold A. 1936 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Fairchild, Henry Platt 1936 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Faris, Ellsworth 1937 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Phelps, Harold A. 1937 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Foreign Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - FINANCES (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - ORGANIZATION - VOL. 1, NO. 1 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - REVIEWS (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Barnes, Harry Elmer 1925-49 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Barnes, Harry Elmer 1950-61 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Barnes, Harry Elmer 1962- (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Barnes, Harry Elmer, Testimonial Volume - Jorelamon, Dorothy (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - CORRESPONDENCE - Barnes, Harry Elmer, Testimonial Volume - Religious Ideas (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Publications and Speeches
  Hankins was a very prolific writer, and the Publications and Speeches series contains almost all of his work. He published many pamphlets on a variety of topics, such as issues of race, population control, and poverty. These are themes that keep recurring through his work. Many of his articles have been published in various newspapers, and these are included as well. It is apparent that Hankins was a progressive thinker who enjoyed challenging existing beliefs.
  - PUBLICATIONS (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - PUB - Adolph Quetelet as Statistician (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - PUB - The Approach to Responsibility (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - PUB - Are Nordics Superior? (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - PUB - Barnes, Harry Elmer, International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - PUB - Biology and Society: Modern Social Organization (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - PUB - Civilization and Fertility (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - PUB - The Conflict of Civilization and Parenthood (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - PUB - The Contributions of Science to Social Work (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - PUB - The Declining Birth Rate (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - PUB - Dictionary of Sociology (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - PUB - Does Advancing Civilization Involve...Fertility? (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - PUB - Editorials (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - PUB - El Libre Albedrio Y El Determinismo (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - PUB - Eugenic Hypothesis (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - PUB - Eugenics and the Culture Drift (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - PUB - Facts and the Nordic Doctrine (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Forty-Year Perspective (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - PUB - Franklin Henry Giddings, 1855-1931 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - PUB - Franklin Henry Giddings (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - PUB - Freedom of Speech and Freedom of Teaching (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - PUB - Further Suggestions Concerning the Content of an Elementary Course (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - PUB - German Policies for Increasing Births (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - PUB - Giddings, Franklin Henry (Box 8, Folder 2)
    See Franklin Henry Giddings
  - PUB - Granville, Stanley Hall 1846-1924 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Hampshire History (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Heredity and Environment (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - PUB - The Historian Must Be Free (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - PUB - How About the Jews? (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - PUB - Humanism and World Consciousness (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - PUB - Humanism and the Culture Stream (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - PUB - Humanitarianism in the Light of Biology (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - PUB - Individual Differences and Democratic Theory (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - PUB - Individual Differences and Their Significance for Social Theory (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - PUB - Individual Differences: The Galton-Pearson Approach (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - PUB - Individual Freedom with Some Sociological Implications of Determinism (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - PUB - Introduction to Sociology (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - PUB - Introduction to the Study of Society, 1st ed. 1928 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - PUB - Introduction to the Study of Society, Rev. ed. 1935 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - PUB - Is Our Innate National Intelligence Declining? (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - PUB - Is the Differential Fertility of the Social Class Selective? (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - PUB - Latest in the Philosophy of History (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - PUB - Meaning of Race and Race Superiority (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - PUB - Migrant Asia by R. Mukerjee (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - PUB - Modern Social Organizations (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - PUB - Morals and Religion (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - PUB - Morgan's La Prehistorie Orientale (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - PUB - New Books on God, Immortality, and Religious Origins (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - PUB - Organic Plasticity Versus Organic Response (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - PUB - Our Load of Defective Genes (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - PUB - Poverty and Birth Control (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - PUB - Patriotism and Peace (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - PUB - Pressure of Population as a Cause of War (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - PUB - Questions for Sociology: An Informal Round Table (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - PUB - Quetelet's Average Man in Modern Scientific Research (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - PUB - Racial Differences and Industrial Welfare (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - PUB - The Rationality of Birth Control (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - PUB - Reason Versus Authority as a Guide to Living (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - PUB - The Reparations Problem and the Dawes Report (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - PUB - Reviews (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - PUB - Rising Tide of Racial Tension (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - PUB - Social Biology (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - PUB - Social Science and Social Action (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - PUB - Sociology (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - PUB - Sociology and Social Guidance Discussion (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - PUB - Students' Ratings of Instruction (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - PUB - Sumner Centenary Volume (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - PUB - Tillich, Paul (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - PUB - Transformations Politiques Recentes Aux Etats-Unis (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - PUB - Under-Developed Areas with Special Reference to Population Reforms (Box 9, Folder 28)